Let's make some Basil ice cream
using this hydroponically grown
basil, and use a recipe from David
Lebovitz The Perfect [Music] Scoop.
Welcome back to the channel, like it says, we're
going to use some hydroponically grown basil,
this is grown in my unit. On my other channel I
talk a bit more about this ArcVerdi Hydroponics
and Gardening, link below, link up here, head over
like and subscribe and all that kind of stuff.
So we're going to take some of this and we're
going to use a recipe from David Lebovitz The
Perfect Scoop, if you don't have this book you
should, it's a really good introduction to ice
cream making, loads of different flavors. You've
got ice cream, Sorbet, Granita, Gelato etc all
stuff like that in here. It's a really handy book
to help you learn "if's, but's and what's" combine
that with obviously all info that I've got on this
channel and it's a great place to get you started.
So basil ice cream I've never made this
before, let's just get on and see what it
says. So we've got the recipe here along
with the full ingredients and breakdown,
it's in a mixture of grams, cups and whatever else
so I'm going to convert this so everyone has what
they need to make this at home. So what are we
going to need, we're going to need.... fine basic
stuff. He does use egg yolks, not going to make
this a custard we're going to use stabilizers,
more scientific approach to this you know,
that's what I prefer. I don't like loads of
egg whites sitting in the fridge forever so
that aside, let's get all our stuff ready.
In here we've got 25g of Fresh Basil, we've got
the 150g of sugar and 250g of our whipping cream,
so so we now are going to blend this
up in to as smooth a puree as possible.
We need to take out half of this basil mixture
and put it in a bowl because to this, we're going
to add the remaining 250ml/g of heavy cream.
Here we go and we're going to stir this up to
get that nicely combined. The next step is to
get this in a pan and get it on there with the
milk and salt so let's get on and do that bit.
Let's get the remaining, super smooth obviously
in that blender the cream is uh starting to just
slightly whip up so it's thickened a little bit.
So into this pan goes the remaining
half of our Basil cream and then
into that we need to add our milk and salt.
I'll put this back in the fridge but because
we're going to use a an ice cream stabilizer
rather than egg yolks we're going to mix the
salt and the stabilizer together just to make
sure that it can hydrate and it not clump up.
So in here we're going to put in our 250
Ml/g of milk, this is 2% milk, like that,
only need a pinch of salt so we're not
going to be able to mix in our stabilizer.
So let's get this and just a teaspoon or
two of sugar because you need to mix your
ice cream stabilizer with something like
sugars or milk powder to stop it clumping.
If you just add your ice cream stabilizer,
whatever type it is, straight into a liquid,
it will clump up and you'll just get lumps
of it and it actually won't do anything. All
you need to do is just put a little tiny bit of
sugar in there, put your ice cream stabilizer,
again this stands for all powdered stabilizers,
just give it a quick mix like that and then
we can put it in and get in there and stir
that up. And now let's get this on the hob.
So let's just swap this over
for a whisk nice and quick,
and get this mixed up. Now what we're doing is
we're heating this to hydrate that stabilizer,
we would have had to heat this to about 70°C using
egg yolks but because we've used the stabilizer
we're going to take this up to 80°C now.
So heating that Basil up has increased the
green color, so we're now just going to start
mixing these together like [Music] that and
the final thing is to grate the lemon zest
in, so let's get that straight in there,
one final quick stir just to make sure that's
all combined and in the fridge that goes.
After your ice cream is completely chilled
down in the fridge you can take it out and
give it a nice good stir, make sure it's
all mixed together, then pop it in your
ice cream machine to churn. This took about 12
minutes in my machine, but once it was ready,
took it out and started dishing up the tub.
The smell was great when I opened it up here and
as you can see from the color, it's really really
nice non-adjusted color here at all so you get to
see exactly what it looks like to me is exactly
what it looks like to you. A little close-up
shot so you can actually see the glorious green
color, little flecks of Basil in there as well.
Basil ice cream from David Lebovitz The Perfect
Scoop, this is a great book if you're just getting
started like I said before, there's a lot of
recipes in here. They're all quite basic or
the majority of them are quite basic, in terms of
they're designed for your average home ice cream
maker you can, once you learn a bit more about
recipes, start modifying these so I actually
made two versions of this I did one with egg yolks
which is exactly as the recipe states and then one
without withstabilizers which is the one I filmed
and interestingly enough the one with egg yolks
has a much less complex flavor because the egg
yolks actually start to add a bit of taste to it.
And this can be a problem with custard based
ice cream, so you start to get the taste of
the egg yolks come through and it starts
to detract from the delicate flavors that
you're trying to bring forward. So in this
case basil, which is a very strong flavor,
it's also a very strong smell as you know it
if you've ever grown Basil or bought it from
the store, you just have to touch it once and
that smell is with you for hours. So having
something like this without the egg yolks in
means you get the real strong natural flavor of
Basil come through. And it's that classic 2:1
ratio of cream to milk. You can go past that
now you don't have to follow those super basic
recipes to create something you can create much
more complex ice creams at home using, you know,
very few additional ingredients if any at all .
So less talk, let's see what it
actually tastes [Music] like ....
It's got a good texture, I'm not going to
say it's perfect texture because it's not,
but it is very good. The flavor of the Basil
is dulled just slightly by the dairy, which is
another common thing and in this kind of situation
it benefits from the dairy because Basil is such a
strong flavor it needs that dairy fat to to bring
it down, tone it down, so it's not blow your head
off Basil beacuse there's a fair amount in here.
But you're left with this subtle lingering taste
of basil and it's, you know, it's delicious. Basil
is delicious this actually would work really well
on something like a savory bread you know,
with strawberries with some balsamic vinegar,
something like that and also something to note,
the lemon rind / lemon zest wherever you're from,
that really makes a difference here. It cuts
through that basil flavor, doesn't really make
it lemon flavored but you can just catch it at
the end, you can just catch that tiny little
bit of lemon come through and it's a delicious
combination, Basil with that touch of lemon.
So this is the first video I've done
using a recipe directly from the book,
if you're interested in seeing others
or other videos like this where I copy
a recipe from a book then do let me know, I've
got a fair few ice cream books to go through.
I appreciate you coming along
and watching me make basil ice
cream from David Lebvitz The Perfect
Scoop, thanks very much for watching
don't forget to like and subscribe and
I'll see you next [Music] time [Music].